<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep in the system - misc</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://romainjacquet.github.io/</id><updated>2021-04-24T22:13:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>the different way of mounting Google drive with your Ubuntu</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/the-different-way-of-mounting-google-drive-with-your-ubuntu.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-24T22:13:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-24T22:13:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Romain JACQUET</name></author><id>tag:romainjacquet.github.io,2021-04-24:/the-different-way-of-mounting-google-drive-with-your-ubuntu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;be a little disappointed with Google drive mount&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I explained it in my &lt;a href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/the-limitation-of-mounting-google-drive-with-nautilus.html"&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, using 
the built-in feature of gnome to mount Google drive have some serious limitations. Here
I describe all the solutions I have tried. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The native solution provided by the GNOME and KDE environments rely on dedicated libraries to wrap the &lt;code&gt;I/Os&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/KDE/kio"&gt;KIO&lt;/a&gt;  for KDE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gio/"&gt;gio&lt;/a&gt; for GNOME&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the same idea for the two libraries, it provides a superset of &lt;code&gt;I/Os&lt;/code&gt; functions that make easier &lt;code&gt;I/Os&lt;/code&gt; on
remote target accessible via HTTP/FTP. Or any other protocols if you write the corresponding extension. The 
goal is to display remote file storage in your window manager, transparent for the end-user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main drawback is that if your application don't use the file dialog of the window manager it don't work.
And there is a lot of case when apps don't use the dialog of the file manager. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qt or KDE pass running on classical Ubuntu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other graphical toolkits like &lt;a href="https://www.tcl.tk/"&gt;Tk&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/10/docs/api/java/awt/package-summary.html"&gt;AWT&lt;/a&gt; for java apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nautilus_config" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/kio-gio-app.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear if your application doesn't linked on GIO or KIO, it don't work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ldd &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;which gnumeric&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;grep gio
    libgio-2.0.so.0 &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; /usr/lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libgio-2.0.so.0 &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;0x00007f6fffcb7000&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
$ ldd &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;which vim&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;grep gio
$ 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: the google drive slave for KIO does not work with Ubuntu 20, 
see &lt;a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/kaccounts-integration/+bug/1864627"&gt;https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/kaccounts-integration/+bug/1864627&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The rclone problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rclone is a tool that is used for all cloud operations. It supports a wide variety
of cloud providers and have a lot of really cools features like &lt;a href="https://rclone.org/commands/rclone_mount/"&gt;mount&lt;/a&gt;.
The approach is very different from KIO/GIO. This is based 
on &lt;a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/filesystems/fuse.html"&gt;FUSE&lt;/a&gt; a
feature of the linux kernel. This is really powerfull compared to the KIO/GIO approach because
you don't need to change the code source of your application. It's just a standard Unix mount. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nautilus_config" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/rclone_mount.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Rclone token renewal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, it sounds great but what's the problem with rclone? 
I used rclone in 2020 and I finally gave up because the mount was frequently break due to token expiration.
The defaults of rclone are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it's a command line tool so it's not as user-friendly as clicking on the nautilus windows manager
  to connect your drive. Rclone setup is done through a text-mode interface. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rclone is more a sysadmin tools than a end-user tools. Many gory details are visible and slow down
  the usage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all the low-level details of the Google storage API are visible. So you have to create and declare rclone
  as an application in the google Console API to have your own &lt;code&gt;client id&lt;/code&gt;. Having your own client id is 
  not required by it is a good practice. It means you have to be familiar
  with Oauth2, Google apps and things like this (even if there is 
  an &lt;a href="https://rclone.org/drive/#making-your-own-client-id"&gt;official documentation for doing it&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to automate the mount you have to create your own systemd user units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I never succeed to  automate the token renewal. It means that
  each time the token expires, I had to re-run the config in text mode :-(. This a &lt;a href="https://forum.rclone.org/t/rclone-google-drive-token-expires-every-week/22502/18"&gt;known problem&lt;/a&gt;. It's the most annoying problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that Rclone will improve all this things because it's so frustating to see that the mount is working very
  well and it is broken one week after. I don't understand why it's so simple to connect with Gnome and why it's 
  complex with Rclone. Maybe future posts for the blog? :-) :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>The limitation of mounting google drive with nautilus</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/the-limitation-of-mounting-google-drive-with-nautilus.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-17T14:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T14:14:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Romain JACQUET</name></author><id>tag:romainjacquet.github.io,2021-04-17:/the-limitation-of-mounting-google-drive-with-nautilus.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;using google drive with nautilus mount have some serious limitations&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The generalization of the cloud storage comes with a lot of promises and
I really like the possibility to access to my personnal files from everywhere:
web, laptop, personnal computer, ...
With my Android smartphone, it's a native feature. With my Ubuntu the feature is
recent and there are serious limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mounting google drive with Nautilus&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years ago I was using &lt;a href="https://rclone.org/"&gt;rclone&lt;/a&gt; to access to my google drive 
files. Rclone have really nice 
&lt;a href="https://rclone.org/commands/rclone_mount/"&gt;mount&lt;/a&gt; feature. But I finally
give up because there is no simple way to automate the login. You always
have difficulties to renew the token.
Here come the nautilus feature that allow you to set oneline account. It's
available from the gnome-control-center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nautilus_browser" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/oneline_accounts.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="nautilus_config" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/nautilus_oneline.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once configured you can access to your google drive files. But I quicky realized that a lot of 
applications didn't work if the files are located on the drive. Gnumeric, gedit are
working but &lt;a href="https://keepassxc.org/"&gt;keepassxc&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.vim.org/"&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt; 
doesn't work at all. With keepassxc it sometimes results in data corruption! With vim
the file is correctly displayed but saving the file failed. Even if the &lt;code&gt;nobackup&lt;/code&gt; option,
some strange errors appeared.
&lt;img alt="nautilus_config" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/vim_error.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Under the hood&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nautilus is using a dedicated library named &lt;a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gio/"&gt;gio&lt;/a&gt; that 
provide all the features to
access to remote drives like google. The official gio description tells 
&lt;strong&gt;provide an API that is so good that developers prefer it over raw POSIX calls&lt;/strong&gt;! I was a little bit surprized 
when I read this :-).
The &lt;a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gio/stable/gio.html"&gt;gio command&lt;/a&gt; allows us 
to manipulate the filesystem from the command line using the gio primitives. Comparing the output
of gio's commands to the standard unix commands (ls, cat) is meaningfull. 
We can understand how gio transform I/O to display the content in nautilus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ls 
17lXzXGnhfA89w39PitPdtblkoOW8t8rA  1HnbYPHAwbchlu1pCMnRS-qxRQtfs4ULO  1LJ9W3ZzmfVMyzE09abGOIswXwdjwI8x2
$ gio list -d
mytext2.txt
kpwd
simpsons
$ gio cat mytext2.txt
toto
titi
tata
tutu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Why some applications work and other don't work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the application use the standard POSIX functions like &lt;code&gt;open&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;write&lt;/code&gt; and manipulate files through
plain-old file descriptors it will not work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the application use the gio library and the gio abstractions like &lt;code&gt;GFile&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;GFileInfo&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;GInputStream&lt;/code&gt; it will
work. When using &lt;code&gt;open&lt;/code&gt; directly on the file exposed by gio mount it will break the file because open is not 
aware that it is a network share. And some attributes like 'standard::display-name' are lost when performing IOs.
&lt;strong&gt;From Nautilus, if you open a file with an application that don't use gio you could corrupt or lost the file&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;the future?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't imagine that all applications will use gio in the future. Gio is intended for Gnome application not for
all the application. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it possible to have a native support for Google Drive in the future? I mean that you can access without any
additionnal library like gio or KIO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it possible for gio to intercept POSIX calls and transform them into GIO call?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure because this is complex. But it could be a better user experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Desktop chair of 2006 VS gaming chair of 2020</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/desktop-chair-of-2006-vs-gaming-chair-of-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-01T14:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T14:48:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Romain JACQUET</name></author><id>tag:romainjacquet.github.io,2020-05-01:/desktop-chair-of-2006-vs-gaming-chair-of-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;dxracer formula08 review&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just after the beginning of the lockdown in France, I started homeworking full time.
I quickly realized that my old computer chair of 2005 was not good enough
to sit from eigth to ten hours per day in front of my computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bougth this chair sixteen years ago when I was a student. It was
fine for years but currently: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the foam of the seat is near to zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I sometime feel some pressure on the elbows. Because armrests are made
with a narrow piece of hard plastic. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is no neck support because the chair back stop after the shoulder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2005 desktop chair" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/old_chair_2005.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordering new chair with the lockdown was not really easy because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delivery is a little bit chaotic and delay could be longer than
two weeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buying a chair online is not really easy. Finding the correct
size is not simple and I spent a lot of time to look at sizing chart of
the different supplyer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose a DxRacer Formula 08 and I was lucky to receive it two days after
 ordering!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2005 desktop chair" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/2020_gaming_chair.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After two weeks of usage, here is the summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the wide and soft armrests are really confortable. The armrest are fully covered 
by a very soft material. I really like it; and now I consider that the 
armrest of my old chair were horrible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the armrest are said &lt;code&gt;3D&lt;/code&gt;. You can adjust the heigth, the angle and the distance
from the back. It is really cool, but I wish I could pull them backward with two or three
additionnal centimeters. I like to work very close from the desktop. Maybe I got shorter arms
than the average :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the neck support and neck pillow are helpfull. Where I read a doc or watch a video,
you can fully lean against the chair back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my gaming chair have a lumbar pillow and I sometimes felt a litte tension in the lumbar
at the end of the day. I had the feeling that the lumbar pillow was too big for me.
Either my back is flatter than the average or my weigth is to low for this pillar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the major difference between a gaming chair and a traditionnal desktop chair is the angle between
the seat and the floor. With gaming chairs the seat is not really flat, there is a small angle. Exactly
like if you were sitting in a sport car, you lean backward. With this position, it's more difficult
 to spread the legs behind the desk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="angle comparaison" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/seat_angle.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy with my new chair. The only problem is the lumbar pillow.
I finally discovered a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/pcmasterrace/comments/am8jmp/dxracer_chair_lumbar_pillow_is_it_okay_not_to_use/"&gt;Reddit post&lt;/a&gt; 
describing the same feeling with the lumbar pillow.
I will probably customize it by removing extra foam inside. There is a zipper and
the foam is easily accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="angle comparaison" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/pillar_foam.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>