<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep in the system - misc</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://romainjacquet.github.io/</id><updated>2020-05-01T14:48:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Desktop chair of 2006 VS gaming chair of 2020</title><link href="https://romainjacquet.github.io/desktop-chair-of-2006-vs-gaming-chair-of-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-01T14:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T14:48:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Romain JACQUET</name></author><id>tag:romainjacquet.github.io,2020-05-01:/desktop-chair-of-2006-vs-gaming-chair-of-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;dxracer formula08 review&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just after the beginning of the lockdown in France, I started homeworking full time.
I quickly realized that my old computer chair of 2005 was not good enough
to sit from eigth to ten hours per day in front of my computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bougth this chair sixteen years ago when I was a student. It was
fine for years but currently: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the foam of the seat is near to zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I sometime feel some pressure on the elbows. Because armrests are made
with a narrow piece of hard plastic. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is no neck support because the chair back stop after the shoulder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2005 desktop chair" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/old_chair_2005.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordering new chair with the lockdown was not really easy because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delivery is a little bit chaotic and delay could be longer than
two weeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buying a chair online is not really easy. Finding the correct
size is not simple and I spent a lot of time to look at sizing chart of
the different supplyer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose a DxRacer Formula 08 and I was lucky to receive it two days after
 ordering!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2005 desktop chair" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/2020_gaming_chair.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After two weeks of usage, here is the summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the wide and soft armrests are really confortable. The armrest are fully covered 
by a very soft material. I really like it; and now I consider that the 
armrest of my old chair were horrible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the armrest are said &lt;code&gt;3D&lt;/code&gt;. You can adjust the heigth, the angle and the distance
from the back. It is really cool, but I wish I could pull them backward with two or three
additionnal centimeters. I like to work very close from the desktop. Maybe I got shorter arms
than the average :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the neck support and neck pillow are helpfull. Where I read a doc or watch a video,
you can fully lean against the chair back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my gaming chair have a lumbar pillow and I sometimes felt a litte tension in the lumbar
at the end of the day. I had the feeling that the lumbar pillow was too big for me.
Either my back is flatter than the average or my weigth is to low for this pillar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the major difference between a gaming chair and a traditionnal desktop chair is the angle between
the seat and the floor. With gaming chairs the seat is not really flat, there is a small angle. Exactly
like if you were sitting in a sport car, you lean backward. With this position, it's more difficult
 to spread the legs behind the desk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="angle comparaison" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/seat_angle.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy with my new chair. The only problem is the lumbar pillow.
I finally discovered a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/pcmasterrace/comments/am8jmp/dxracer_chair_lumbar_pillow_is_it_okay_not_to_use/"&gt;Reddit post&lt;/a&gt; 
describing the same feeling with the lumbar pillow.
I will probably customize it by removing extra foam inside. There is a zipper and
the foam is easily accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="angle comparaison" src="https://romainjacquet.github.io/images/pillar_foam.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>